Many organizations use a project management office it's a way to coordinate projects in a particular
area.
So in a department in the whole company or just within you know a small group or type of work typically
Primos are within departments.
So the I.T. Department could have its own PMO.
It's possible that a larger company that you have a PMO for all projects in the organization.
Either way really doesn't matter for your exam what you'll need to know the characteristics of a PMO
and are you working with the PMO.
How does that affect you as the project manager.
So let's look at the characteristics here.
So a project management office.
Their first goal is to support project managers helps to manage shared resources across the PMO.
So resources being equipment facilities tools but also people.
They may help coordinate when people can be utilized on what projects Piccolo's can provide some coaching
mentoring and training for project managers.
Because what people most often want is a uniform approach to doing projects so that all projects in
this organization take the same approach follow the same processes.
Use the same forms and tools and techniques for all projects so that stakeholders know what to expect.
Their uniformity across the projects and it's a repeatable approach to project management project management
offices might also conduct project audits where we want to confirm that the projects are adhering to
these repeatable approaches that have been established are using they being project managers and the
project team are using the right tools and techniques are using the right forms or templates using the
right software.
So a project audit is a way of not just financial audit but that you are doing the work as planned as
your prescribed in that PMO.
PMO is also responsible for developing and managing processes and procedures so just what I was talking
about there that we have a particular way and how to communicate and we use these forms and you have
to set out a status report every Thursday and you have to have a status meeting at least every other
week or you have to create this form for procurement or change requests.
Follow this approach.
So all projects have the same approach in that organization.
And thats actually a really great thing for a project manager for a couple of reasons one it saves time
but I dont have to reinvent the wheel every time that I go into a project and I don't have to train
stakeholders on how we do change control or what forms to expect and when everybody knows whenever we
do a project you're going to get a status report on Thursday.
We're having a status meeting Monday morning and that will set out our goal for the week.
And we're going to be using these forms and this is how you get change control the types of questions.
So it really speeds up some of that just the oversight of project management by using a PMO and having
established approaches.
So I like working with the PMO.
It also helps communication across projects especially if you're in an organization where project team
members come from all over.
They might be on multiple projects at once.
So it helps you to communicate with other project managers and to schedule resources physical and human.
There are three types of project offices you want to be familiar with you have supportive controlling
and directive a supportive.
Just like it sounds like they're more of a consultation of role where they are helping the project manager
and consulting giving templates and training.
Controlling is more about compliance that you have to work to a framework and use specific forms of
specific templates and follow this governance and then directive typically means that the project is
owned by the PMO the project manager works as part of the PMO.
So they manage the project and they control the project lifecycle.
So it's not distributed or spread across different groups.
Everything all projects can be asked for by different groups but once they start or get initiated they're
part of the PMO.
So they really control everything as far as the project lifecycle approach.
It's important to know these were your exam because depending on what type of PMO you're in that will
affect how you manage the project.
All right.
Good job.
I'll see you in the next lecture.